Girls, please get ready.
接下来是女同学
The next group includes students whose student number is from 1160201
学号一一六零二零一
to 116220.
到一一六二二零准备
Is it Qing's turn now?
轮到小晴了吗
She's in the next group.
下一组就是她们了
Yesterday Sa came to see me.
昨天小撒又找我了
Er.
嗯
He also keeps
他也天天锲而不舍
texting me every day.
给我发信息呢
So you didn't change
你还像以前那样
your decision?
的决定吗
Or what?
那不然呢
I'd rather use the time to eat hot pot
火锅不好吃吗
and watch TV.
电视剧不好看吗
I'm not that silly. Go and lose competitions? It's not fun at all.
没事去输比赛找罪受啊
Don't worry, Qing.
没事 小晴
Fanfan and I will help you.
一会儿我和凡凡带着你
Sorry, I can't.
我不行
I want to break the records.
我要拿个破纪录的
Come on.
你们加油
I'll help you.
没事 我带着你
Ow!
哎呀
It's okay. I won't give up on you.
没事 我不会放弃你的
I'll help you.
走吧 我带着你一起
Just run yourself, or we'll all fail.
这样大家都挂科了
It's okay.
没事
Come on.
加油
Just run yourself.
你们先跑吧 别管我了
No, no, no.
别别别 别别别
Hold on, hold on.
坚持住 坚持住
We won't give up on you.
不会放弃你的
We've taken a lap.
一圈了 一圈了
Or we'll all fail the exam.
要不大家都挂科了
Hey.
喂
What are you doing?
你拉我干嘛
Come on, Qing.
加油 小晴
Come on, Qing. We'll run with you.
加油 小晴 陪你跑
Come on.
来 加油
Come on. Come on.
加油 加油
What are they doing?
他们干什么呢
Run with us. We run too?
你们也跑 我们也跑
Come on. Come on.
加油 加油
Come on.
加油
Come on, Qing.
加油 小晴
Come on. Come on.
加油 加油
We've finished.
过了 过了
Lu Wenqing. Four minutes and twenty-three seconds.
陆雯晴 四分二十三秒
Pass just right.
正好及格
You passed!
过了 过了
I never expected to
我做梦也想不到
pass the 800-meter exam.
有一天能跑完八百米
I also never expected that
我也没有想到
it could be so fun
原来跑八百米
to run 800 meters.
也能这么开心
Don't get me wrong.
不是我说啊
But you girls are so weird.
你们女孩也太奇怪了
What's the point of
那跑个八百米
running together?
还得同进同出的
You know nothing about girls' friendship.
女生的友谊你懂什么
I understand.
我理解
It's awesome.
特别燃
In fact, I may
其实我之前可能就有点
have made a little too much of a fuss before.
太小题大做了
Now, I've finished it.
那我完成了之后发现
It is no big deal.
也没什么嘛
As long as we screwed up our courage,
果然只要鼓起勇气
nothing is impossible.
什么都能做得到
My name's You Mengyuan.
我叫游梦圆
I think you are very pretty.
我觉得你很有气质
When do you have time?
你什么时候有时间
I wonder if you
不知道你愿不愿意
want to see a movie with me?
和我一起看个电影
Does he just ask her out?
算是做了
Yeah.
嗯
Will he get a chance?
有戏吗
I don't think so.
悬
Towel?
毛巾要吗
20 yuan.
二十一条
Where's Mengyuan?
梦圆呢
Who knows?
谁知道啊
Maybe his expression of love was refused
告白失败
and he's crying in the corner.
躲哪个角落哭呢吧
Xiaoyu
小鱼啊
I want to say something to you.
我有件事想跟你说
Me, too.
我也有事想跟你说
Thank you for helping me today.
今天谢谢大家
Enjoy yourselves.
大家吃好 喝好
Well.
来
Cheers!
干杯
Do me a favor.
给个面子
Okay.
好
Do you remember ......
你还记不记得
Let's go together next time.
要不然下次一起去
Shall we go somewhere else?
要不换一家
Have more.
多吃点
What a coincidence.
还真是够巧的
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Yin Nan, are you threatening me?
殷楠威胁我是吧
Don't get me wrong.
别误会
I didn't except to meet you here.
遇到你们真是意外
As for Tony,
至于托尼呢
I heard that yesterday someone was sneaking
我昨天听说宿舍门前
in front of the dormitory
有人鬼鬼祟祟地
and was doing something weird.
不知道在干什么
I'm afraid that it may be stolen.
我担心是有贼在惦记它
For the sake of its safety,
我为了它的安全着想
I take it
这几天
with me wherever I go.
我都尽量随身带着它
Don't play innocent!
别装受害人了行吗
It was you who
我儿子是你
picked up my pet, right?
捡回来的对吧
You got it two weeks ago, didn't you?
两周前捡回来的对吧
You know it clearly
你自己心里很清楚
whether I'm telling the truth or not.
我说的是不是实话
Even if you are telling the truth,
就算你说的是真的
I want to ask you that
我想问一下
how irresponsible
是多么不负责任
are you
没有常识的主人
to lose the pet turtle.
会让自己的宠物龟跑掉
It is not as naughty as a Husky.
这不是哈士奇撒手没
This is a pet turtle.
这宠物龟
Its last owner
如果它的上一任
abandoned it,
主人遗弃它
and I adopted it.
我把它收养了
Any problems?
有什么问题
Yin Nan
殷楠
It was me who lost it.
小小鱼是我弄丢的
It's not Xiaoyu's fault.
这事不怪小鱼
You two have known each other
你们两个认识不是
for quite a long time.
一两天了吧
She knew clearly that you are careless
她明知道你粗心大意
and still let you look after the turtle.
还把乌龟交给你照顾
She is irresponsible, too.
我指责她有错吗
It's my fault.
这件事是我不对
Whatever,
不论如何
the turtle is innocent.
小小鱼是无辜的
You can ask me to do anything,
你让我做什么都行
as long as you give it back to Xiaoyu.
但请你把乌龟还给小鱼
You make me
你说得我像是
sound like an unreasonable villain.
不讲道理的恶人一样
There's no evidence
现在并没有证据
can prove directly that
能够直接证明
my Tony is your Little Xiaoyu.
托尼它就是小小鱼
Sorry, I can't give it to you.
请恕我不能答应
I've got an idea.
我有一个主意
How about let Little Xiaoyu
让小小鱼
make the choice itself.
自己选择怎么样
Little Xiaoyu
小小鱼
Tony
托尼
Come here.
这儿
Okay. It only works for dogs.
好吧 这招只对狗有效
Today,
今日
you and me,
你我之间
only one can take it home.
只有一个人能带它走
What do you want to do?
你想怎么办吧
Calm down. Calm down. Calm down.
冷静 冷静 冷静
What're you doing?
干嘛呢
Don't be
你们能不能别动不动
so emotional
就舞刀弄枪
and play so rough.
刀光剑影的啊
This is a public place. We need to settle this
公共场合找点
in a serious way.
严肃的方式解决
Okay?
好不好
So what should
你说
we do, now?
怎么办
Hey.
哎
I have seen
我在这边啊
what's going on there.
也看了半天热闹了
I have a solution for you.
我这边有个解决方案
This "Super Spicy Duel"
这个超级热辣对决呢
is a tradition of our restaurant.
是本店的传统
In front of you are
你们面前分别是
three kinds of chili sauce
跳脚辣 爆炸辣
which are extra spicy, super spicy and deadly spicy.
和地狱辣三种辣酱
The one who can eat three French fries
能够在五分钟之内
dipped in the chili sauce one by one
依次吃完
within five minutes
蘸满辣椒的三根薯条
and not drink water in 30 seconds
然后三十秒内不能喝水
will be free of charge for this meal.
当餐免单
May I remind you of a little something I'd like to call?
可别怪我没提醒大家哟
Nobody has succeeded
开店到现在
since I opened the restaurant.
还没有挑战成功的人
Little Xiaoyu will
小小鱼
belong to the one who wins.
就归赢的那个人走
I say it one last time
我最后说一遍
its name is Tony.
它叫托尼
It has nothing to do with you.
这件事跟你没关系
I won't let you
我是绝对不会让学姐你
fight alone.
孤军奋战的
I finally get a chance
我终于有机会弥补
to make amends for
把小小鱼
losing Little Xiaoyu.
丢了的过失了
You can rest assured that
你放心
I'll do my best.
我会全力以赴
I'm here with you!
我在你身边
And I'm here with Senior Yin Nan.
而学姐身边有我
Ready.
预备
Go!
开始
Just so so.
感觉一般嘛
Yeah.
是啊
Stop your bravado.
别死撑了
Your face is as red as the cherries.
你脸红得跟樱桃似的
As red as cherries.
红得跟樱桃似的
So what?
又怎么样
You are drenched with sweat
那也比你满头大汗
and have your eyes filled with tears.
眼含热泪强
What's the matter? Is your life too hard?
怎么了 生活太苦了吗
Those are
那是对你这个
tears of pity for you loser.
败者怜悯的泪水
Here comes the spiciest one.
第三关来了
I can even
这个辣椒
feel the spiciness here.
这么远都辣眼睛
Countdown begins.
倒计时
Ten.
十
Nine.
九
Eight.
八
Seven.
七
Six.
六
Five.
五
Four.
四
Water.
水
I win!
我赢了
You make it!
赢了赢了赢了
Does it make any sense of winning me in eating spicy food?
吃辣算什么本事
Of course.
当然算了
I once thought that
我以为我这辈子
I would never stand a chance to win you.
赢不了你
But now I got you in eating spicy food.
但是吃辣上面我赢你了
Give my baby back to me!
你把我儿子还我
You should admit your failure.
愿赌服输啊
Little Xiaoyu is ours now.
小小鱼归我们了
My baby.
儿子
Water. Get some water.
水 快倒水
Be careful.
慢点慢点
You have acute gastroenteritis.
急性肠胃炎
The doctor said
医生说
it is because
是因为
you have eaten too much spicy food.
吃了太多辣的引起的
It is worthwhile.
值
What did you
你刚才
want to say to me in the restaurant?
想跟我说什么来着
You must have guessed it.
你猜到了吧
Then let's talk to Sa tomorrow.
那明天一起找小撒吧
How did you think it through?
你是怎么想开的
I've promised you
我早就答应过你
to win the champion together with you.
要陪你一起拿冠军
How could I forget
答应过你的事
my promise?
我怎么能忘呢
It is you
倒是你啊
who firmly refused to join the team again.
之前那么坚定
I used to think that
我以前觉着吧
no matter how hard you try,
有些事不管你怎么努力
little difference would be made on some matters.
都也没啥用
Now Qing has overcome her greatest difficulty.
现在小晴的事一出
It suddenly occurred to me
突然就明白了
that I'd better give it a shot again.
还是试一试吧
Maybe I'll make it.
万一成功了呢
Right?
是吧
Okay.
好
Then
那以后
I'm still the captain of our team.
我还是你们的队长
Good.
好
Finally,
终于啊
our team will be back in the arena.
我们队重出江湖
Er.
诶
Do we need to
那我们是不是
go to the previous classroom for training?
还要去之前的教室训练
Will we get training together with Team One?
会跟他们一起吗
Dango
团子
Could you please dream bigger
能不能长点出息啊
and find a better example?
提高点审美行不行
Okay.
好了
I now declare that
我宣布
Debate Team Two
全员到齐
is officially established.
辩论队二队正式成立
Yeah!
耶
Give ourselves a big round of applause!
可以鼓掌了
Well.
您看
What's the schedule for the next training session
接下来的比赛日程
and training classroom for Team Two?
和训练教室怎么安排
By the way,
对了
in addition to
除了平时的日常
the daily competitions,
比赛之外
I'd like to invite
我还想邀请一下
debate teams from other schools
其他学校的辩论队
to compete with Team Two.
来跟我们二队切磋一下
After all, this team
毕竟这支队伍
still needs to be polished.
还是需要继续打磨的
As for the training classroom,
那个训练教室啊
you may share it with Team One.
你就和一队
You two teams can use it together.
一块用就行了
And the rest of the arrangements,
剩下的事情
you may listen to Team One.
就听从一队安排
Listen ......
听
Listen to Team One?
听一队安排
Yeah.
对啊
You Team Two
不是 你们二队
is supposed to serve the Team One.
就是给一队服务的嘛
Nan Bei and Xiaoyu
南北和小鱼
will kill me, if they know this.
一定会弄死我的
Today, the school officially issued a notice that
今日学校正式下发通知
the registration of CET-4
英语四级将于
will begin this week.
本周开始报名
At the meeting, the secretary of the party committee of the university
校党委书记
once again stressed
在会上再次强调
the importance of English proficiency
大学生英语
of college students
水平的重要性
and asked teachers in charge of each grade
并要求各年级负责老师
to strictly supervise students to enter for the exam.
严格把关英语
Here is a report from our correspondent in the university.
下面请看详细报道
Now let's listen to
现在我们来听听
the students' opinions.
同学们的看法
Here comes a boy.
这里就有一位
Good morning. May I ask you a question?
请问同学
Do you have any thoughts
你对四级考试临近
on the approach of CET-4?
有什么看法吗
Stop it. Stop it.
别录了 别录了
Er.
哎
Good morning.
同学
The CET-4 is approaching.
请问四级考试就要到了
Are you well-prepared?
你开始准备复习了吗
He may be busy with
其他同学可能还有
his review plans.
自己的准备计划
Let's interview
让我们来看一下
this girl here.
这位同学
Good morning.
同学
The CET-4 is coming next week.
下周就要考四级了
How are you getting on with your preparation?
你准备得怎么样了
CET-4.
四级
CET ......
四
Mengyuan
梦圆
What kind of pre-workout are you taking?
你这喝的什么氮泵啊
You are exercising so hard.
练这么猛
Someone interviewed me
我今天出门
today and
有人采访我
asked me whether I feel nervous
问我马上考四级
for the approaching CET-4?
了紧张吗
I ......
我
So I get nervous now.
所以我紧张了
Are you kidding me, bro?
有没有搞错 大哥
Your English is so good.
你不是成绩挺好的吗
Don't be nervous.
你慌什么呀
You don't understand.
你知道什么呀
As a genius,
作为一名天才
bearing the tend to go overboard on one subject
偏科是
is a basic feature, okay?
基本的配置 好嘛
If I hadn't
要不是当年
bet on the right English composition topic in the exam,
我英语作文押对了题
I really wouldn't have a chance to be here.
咱真没机会当兄弟
You Mengyuan
游梦圆
What are you doing?
你干嘛呢你
Put your clothes on.
把衣服赶紧穿上
The opposite is the girls' dormitory.
对面是女生寝室
You don't know it?
你不知道啊
I'm not afraid of being seen by them.
我不怕被她们看
I'm afraid you'll flash people's eyes blind.
我怕你闪瞎别人的眼睛
Mr. Li, have some water please.
李主任 喝水
No, thanks.
别别
I'm not thirsty.
不用 我喝过了
Ma Nan
马楠
Stop the game.
别玩了 别玩了
Pause here.
暂停一下
The CET-4 is approaching.
四级报名的事情
You know it, right?
知道了吧
Ah.
啊
Be sure to enter for the exam this time, okay?
再不报就大六了
You haven't registered yet?
你还没报
Shut up.
去去
Well, Mr. Li.
不是 老李
I just knew the news
我知道这事
two minutes ago.
才没到两分钟呢
May you
你让我
give me some time to think about it?
回头研究一下好吧
How much time do you want?
你回头 你回哪个头啊
Just take the exam this time.
明天赶紧考试
After the exam, you leave here
考完走人
and we'll never see each other again.
不要再见面了
Do you get it?
知道吗
Yeah.
知道了
As the dorm monitor,
作为寝室长
you need to urge everyone to make progress.
这屋子都什么人
Separate dry and wet garbage.
干湿垃圾分一下
Okay. Okay.
好嘞 好嘞
Okay.
好嘞
Well. I'm leaving now.
好了 走了
See you, Mr, Li.
慢走啊 李主任
Welcome you to come again.
常来啊
I never expected that
没想到
your weakness is English.
你弱点是英语啊
Don't mention it.
别提了
Even now, I have nightmares
我到现在做噩梦啊
about my English college entrance examination.
梦见我英语高考啊
Er.
哎呀
I dreamed about the English Listening Comprehension part.
说考英语听力
I turned the paper forward
我把卷面往前一翻
and guess what?
你猜怎么着
You didn't know the answers at all.
一道也不会
It was finished before the listening material was played.
我英语听力写完了
Er.
哎
Our university is
财大怎么着
one of the top universities.
也是个九八五
How could you get admitted by our university?
你怎么考进来的
I got a full score in the comprehensive science test.
我理综满分啊
You got a full score in the comprehensive science test while you chose the Department of Law?
理综满分你考一法律系
Well.
哎呀
Have you watched Legal High?
你看过《胜利即正义》吗
So childish.
幼稚
You say me childish?
你还说我呢
Look at yourself.
你看你
You are not a shrewd person.
怎么看也不像精明的人
Why did you choose to learn economics?
为什么要学经济
Have you watched Hanzawa Naoki?
你看过《半泽直树》吗
Oh.
哦哦
But we have
不过我们对于
very similar aesthetic
男人的审美上
for men.
还是比较一致的
In order to improve your English skills,
为了提高你的英语
from now on,
现在开始
let's talk in English.
咱俩用英语交流吧
What?
别呀
We should be on the same page now.
咱们现在应该一致对外
Stop embarrassing each other.
别内讧了
Today, we're going to
咱们今天可是
challenge Team One.
踢馆去的
Yeah.
嗯
Sorry.
对不起
Though we are Team Two,
虽然咱们现在是二队
we can't lose in momentum.
但气势上不能输
You are right.
没错
They will certainly
还不知道那两个要
laugh at us.
怎么嘲笑咱们呢
"You see see you."
你看看你
"Uncle know
叔叔知道
make me birth gas."
给我做出生气体
What're you talking about in English?
你英语说什么呢
What is "birth gas"?
什么是出生气体
Get angry. (The pronunciation of "birth gas" is similar to "get angry" in Chinese.)
生气啊
What is "uncle know"?
叔叔知道呢
Know exactly. (The pronunciation of "uncle know" is similar to "know exactly" in Chinese.)
就知道啊
They did a great job setting up here.
他们把这儿整挺好的
It's used for training.
训练就训练呗
Why did they put so many trophies here?
摆这么多奖杯干嘛呀
Where's our stuff?
咱们的东西呢
Here.
在这儿呢
Thank God they didn't touch my stuff
得亏没碰我东西
or I'll kill them.
要不然我弄死他们
This is my Mr. Green-hat.
我的绿帽子先生
Cute, right?
可爱吧
What a
你什么
weird name!
取名字的品味啊
You know nothing.
你懂什么呀
Come here.
过来 来
Come and
跟姐姐玩一场
play this with me.
你最喜欢的绿帽子游戏
What?
什么
Come here.
过来
As our old rules,
老规矩来
the one who loses first.
输了的人先
You press this one.
你按这个呀
Dare you press this or not?
你敢不敢按这个
Not this one. Go on.
不是 来
Oh my god!
我的妈呀
One more time.
再来一次 再来一次
We ......
我
We are members of Team Two.
我们是二队队员
Xiaoyu. Nan Bei.
小鱼 南北
You are the Team Two.
你们就是二队的队员
Where's your instructor?
你们指导老师呢
How are you, Mr. Meng?
你好 孟老师
I'm Sa.
我是小撒
How's the way of my showing up?
我这个出场怎么样啊
Ah?
啊
We can't lose in momentum.
气势上不能输啊
You can call me Mr. Meng.
我姓孟
I'm the instructor of Team One.
是一队的带队教练
May I give you a brief introduction
我简单介绍一下
of the condition of Team One this year.
一队今年的情况
Three months later,
三个月以后
the Provincial Debate League will be held.
就是全省辩论联赛
Last year we lost to
去年我们在决赛上
South Jiaotong University in the final.
输给了南交大
So this year
所以今年
we only have one goal
一队只有一个目标
that is gain the championship.
就是夺冠
This year, the provincial competition
今年的省赛呢
has changed its rules.
跟以往不同
For the past two years,
这两年
there are
咱们省内
more and more debate teams
各个院校的辩论队
in universities of our province.
数量越来越多
And small-scale competitions
小型比赛
are becoming more and more mature.
办得也是越来越成熟
Therefore, based on the actual situation,
所以根据实际情况
this year's provincial preliminary rounds
今年的省赛初赛环节
will no longer organize centralized competitions,
将不再组织集中比赛
but will organize free-point competitions
而是在三个月赛季内
within three months of the season.
进行自由积分赛
Only those teams with enough points
拿到足够的积分
can goes through to
才能够进入
the grand final and
最后的决赛
compete for the championship next year.
在明年争夺冠军
Mr. Meng
报告老师
What is the free-point competition?
什么叫自由积分赛啊
It seems to
这和你们二队
have nothing to do with you Team Two.
好像没有什么关系吧
Well.
这个
The free-point competition means that
这个自由积分赛了
we need to
就是通过
take part in various competitions
自己报名不同的比赛
and accumulate points.
拿到积分
It is similar to course selection.
和大家选课一样
It is up to you
选什么课
to select your own courses
由你们自己决定
as long as you can get enough credits.
学分够了就可以
So as long as the competitions are officially recognized,
只要是官方认可的比赛
we can gain corresponding points according to their different levels
根据不同的等级
by attending them.
就可以算作积分
Generally speaking,
一般来说
if you win the competition, you'll get three points
赢得三分
and if lose, you'll get one point.
输得一分
If we can get 50 points,
拿到五十分
we'll participate in the finals.
就可以进入决赛圈
Then we need to take part in so many competitions.
那得打多少比赛啊
I know that you haven't
由于二队的各位
participated in provincial competitions yet.
都没有参加过省赛
So, based on the competition experience
所以我会根据过往
with other teams,
和这些队伍比赛的经验
I'll select appropriate teams
为你们挑选出
for you as reference.
合适的队伍作为参考
Of course, I will also take into consideration
当然也会考虑到
your current abilities.
你们目前的实力
So,
所以呢
I hope that
我们就要劳烦
Team Two will take part in
二队的同学们
as many competitions as possible
多多比赛
to accumulate points
积累积分
so that Team One will have more time
让一队有更多的时间
to prepare for the final
准备比赛
and win honor for our university.
为学校争得荣誉
In a word,
总之
we'll work together
咱们一起尽力
to win honor for our university.
为学校争得荣誉
Next,
下面呢
the members of our two teams
两个队的同学呀
may give a self-introduction
就做个自我介绍
to get to know each .......   Not now.
相互的熟 不用了
Not now.
不用了
We get plenty of time in the future to know each other.
以后有的是时间
Yanze
彦泽
Here are some competitions
这里面有我近期
I select
为你们二队
for you Team Two.
挑选的合适的比赛
You are welcome.
不用客气
Er.
诶
This is for you.
这杯是给你的
What would you like to drink, you two?
二位需要喝点什么
I didn't order anything, either.
我也没有点啊
You've been
自从你上次光临
blacklisted
本店之后
permanently
已经被
since your last visit.
永久地列为黑名单
And you can't
而且失去了
order on your own in our restaurant any more.
自主点单的机会
This soft drink is
这杯就是为你特制的
specially prepared for you.
无酒精饮料
Hey.
嘁
You must be joking.
你看不起我是不
No.
是
Then
那你们店里
you'd better
这个欢乐时光
give me
这个活动
an extra drink.
得多送我一杯饮料
Okay.
好
I want a cola
那我要一杯可乐
with extra lemon.
多加柠檬
Me too. Thank you.
我也要 谢谢
Okay.
好
So mean.
小气
What competitions are there?
这都是些什么比赛啊
"Wuyuan County Farm Cup"
五原县养殖场杯
College Debate Competition.
大学生辩论赛
Maybe we need to
去这个地方
take the train, tricycle
怕不是得坐火车三轮
and a donkey cart to go there.
外加驴车吧
The transportation of villages is quite convenient now.
现在都村村通了
Well, how about others?
没事 再看看别的吧
There is a district-level competition here.
这不有一场区大赛吗
Really?
是吗
Then let's attend this one.
那我们就去这场吧
Wait.
等会儿
There is a row of small words below.
这下边有排小字
Special thanks to
特别鸣谢商家
Braised Chicken Rice.
黄焖鸡米饭
Oh, my!
哎呀
It is so sour.
真酸呐
It is so ridiculous.
真实的心灵写照吧
These competitions
这些比赛
are not nearly as good as
还没我上高中时候的
the debates
辩论大赛
I had in high school.
质量高呢
It's okay.
不要抱怨了
After all, these are provincial preliminary contests.
毕竟是省内的预赛
They won't be that bad.
水平不会太次的
I assure you with my personality
我以队长的人格
and experience.
和经验保证
Believe me.
相信我
Now,
下面进入
one-on-one debate may begin.
一对一攻辩环节
The debaters may get started.
有请双方辩手
Regarding the rationality of this phenomenon,
关于这个现象的合理性
I don't think it is necessary to discuss it again.
我觉得没有必要再讨论
Because what exists is reasonable.
因为存在即合理
Is that right?
对不对
No.
不对啊
Ah?
啊
Is there anything wrong with that?
有什么问题吗
How could you say no?
你怎么能说不对呢
It is totally right.
这句话本来就是对的呀
Of course, I have the right
我当然有权利
to doubt any of
质疑您方的
your opinions.
任何论据了
Who said
请问存在即合理
"what exists is reasonable"?
这句话是谁说的
As an old saying goes ......
俗话说
It originated from
这句话最早
Hegel's
出自黑格尔的
Philosophy of Right.
法哲学原理
The original one is
原话是
"what is rational
凡是合乎理性的东西
is actual
都是现实的
and what is actual
凡是现实的东西
is rational."
都是合乎理性的
Later French philosopher Sartre
后来法国哲学家萨特
also said similar words.
也说过类似的话
But the existence here
但这里的存在
refers to actuality
都是现实性
and the reason here means rationality.
而合理都是理性的意思
It is far more different
与您说的道德
from what you said
和社会规则中的
the reasons
合乎情理的合理
in social rules.
完全是两个意思
If the phenomenon of repeating the baseless assertion
以讹传讹
can be explained with "what exists is reasonable"
都用存在即合理
to eliminate the unreasonable things
来消解现实生活中的
in daily life.
大量不合理
Is this really reasonable to do so?
这样真的合理吗
So shall we
您看我们是不是有必要
discuss first
先讨论一下这个
the rationality of the phenomenon?
现象的合理性呢
They are too weak.
太弱了
Hao
小好姐
The competitions we'll participate in
咱们以后打比赛
won't be all like this, will they?
不会都是这种水平吧
Probably not.
应该不会
They can be much worse.
应该会比这更菜
Here. Here.
来来来
Come here and get coupons please.
扫码领优惠券
Welcome to Wencheng County
欢迎来到文成县大学生
College Student Debate Competition.
辩论赛的比赛现场
First, let's warmly welcome
我们首先有请
the sponsor of this competition, Mr. Cang,
本届大赛的赞助商
the chairman of the Board of Directors of
文成校区南区宿舍
Shaxian Snack Catering Group,
二号楼东五十米
which is 50 meters east of Building 2,
沙县小吃门店
South District Dormitory,
餐饮集团董事局主席
Wencheng Campus.
沧先生为大赛致辞
When talking about debate,
咱们说起来辩论会
let's talk about food first.
咱们得先说说吃
Why?
为什么呢
Because food is the first necessity of the people.
民以食为天
Right?
对不对呀
Yeah.
对对对 对的
For ancient China, if state governance
如果说经邦伟业
doesn't have agriculture as its foundation,
覆盖了农耕小家
it is tantamount to
那就等于直接
a direct denial of the economic foundation,
否认了经济基础
which is the bedrock of development.
给予的前提发展性
So aren't you
对方辩友口中
denying that
难道不是变相否认了
the economic base
经济基础决定
determines the superstructure?
上层建筑吗
Today,
咱们这次
before the "Noodles Cup" Debate get started,
参加这个拉面杯
I only want to tell you one thing
我只想说一句
that you all need to work very hard
你们都好好干
and be like noodles
就像拉面一样
which bears excellence in color, aroma and taste.
做它个色香味俱全
All creations you have just mentioned
刚才对方辩友所说万物
have their explicit definitions.
都有一个明确的定义
So I am wondering that
那么请问
these definitions exist from the very beginning
这些定义是原本存在
or are created by us human beings
还是由身为人类的我们
subjectively.
主观赋予的呢
Assuming that human beings will be extinct hundreds of years later,
假设几百年后人类灭绝
how should we
那么请问这些
explain the definitions of
万物的定义
all creations?
又该如何解释呢
Why can they
凭什么他们
use more room than us?
占那么大地方
It's time to do something.
是时候做出反抗了
Four copies, please.
复印四份
Er.
哎
Your hands don't work or
你是手不好使
your brain doesn't work?
还是脑子不好使
You can't use the printer yourself?
用不了打印机
Just want to give you something to do
不是为了给
so you won't get bored.
你们二队找点事干吗
We have
我们二队
plenty of things to do.
有的是事情要干
There are competitions we need to prepare for.
我们还要准备辩论赛呢
Which one?
哪一场
The competitions
这周参加的
with the lowest level you've attend this week?
末流水平那几场吗
You make us
你们果然
attend this kind of debates
是为了报复我们
to get back at us, don't you?
才让我们去这些的吧
The duty of you Team Two
二队存在的意义
is to
就是为了
accumulate points for Team One.
给一队攒积分的
With your current strength,
以你们现在的实力
if you want to get points,
要想获得积分
these are the most appropriate ones.
也就剩这些比赛了
Xiaoyu. Calm down. Calm down.
小鱼 冷静 冷静 冷静
Don't let your emotions get the best of you.
千万别被情绪左右
Calm down. Calm down.
人急我缓 人进我退
I'll do this.
我来吧
I'll do it.
我去
Four copies, right?
四份是吧
Wait a moment please.
稍等一下哦
I'll do it now.
我知道了
Four copies.
你们要的四份资料
Forget it.
算了
Captain of Team Two
二队队长
I've emailed to you
下一阶段
the competitions your team can attend
可以报名的比赛
the next stage.
我已经发到你们邮箱了
The Third "Frog Cup" Debate.
第三届田鸡杯
The Sixth "Chocolate Planet Cup" Debate.
第六届巧克力星球杯
We won't participate in this kind of debates.
我们不打这种比赛
What do you mean?
你什么意思
We must participate in the kind of debates
我们要打
you are preparing now.
你们桌子上那种比赛
You are not
我们的比赛
capable enough to participate in this kind of debates.
跟你们的任务目标不符
Who said that?
谁说的
I said.
我说的
You got a problem?
有意见
Yeah.
有
We'll have a response training this afternoon.
下午反应训练
If you don't afraid of embarrassing yourself,
不怕丢脸的话
you can come.
一起来呗
During response training,
反应对抗训练
both sides refute the opinions of each other
双方驳斥对方观点
and you should response immediately.
必须立刻做出反应
The one who hesitates more than half a second will lose.
迟疑半秒以上算输
The one who randomly choose the topic will be team AFF.
抽辩题者为正方
The debate topic is
辩题为
silence is gold.
沉默是金
Start!
开始
The world is complicated and the life is hard to explain.
世界复杂人生厚重
In the face of many things,
面对许多事情
language is too weak to make a difference.
语言都是苍白无力的
So silence is more adoptable.
所以沉默更加可贵
Objection!
反对
Language is not weak at all.
语言并不无力
On the contrary, it is by means of language that human beings can communicate with each other,
相反是语言带来的沟通
so that the weak individuals
让无力的个体
can become a strong community.
成为有力的集体
A community may be stronger than an individual,
集体当然是有力的
but it can't solve
但是却不能解决
all problems.
所有的问题
On many conditions,
很多情况下
we just have to be wordless,
我们就是无言以对
don't we?
不是吗
So, on what kind of problem,
那请问什么问题
should we be wordless
是用无言以对
to solve it?
来解决的呢
Time is up.
时间到
Again.
再来
Start!
开始
Silence means refusing to communicate.
沉默是拒绝沟通
How could the refusal of communication
为什么拒绝沟通
be seen as valuable?
反而是可贵的呢
Does silence always mean a refusal to communicate?
沉默一定是拒绝沟通吗
Silence can be
沉默可以是
"looking at each other wordlessly with tears trickling down the cheeks",
相顾无言唯有泪千行
"holding hands with tears in eyes,
也可以是竟无语凝噎
we can't say a word but all choked up."
执手相看泪眼
and "Silent is Cambridge tonight!". (These lines are from famous Chinese poems.)
更可以是今晚的康桥
What a beautiful love story!
这样美丽的爱情
Isn't it valuable?
它不可贵吗
Love is fleeting
爱情转瞬即逝
while gold can exist for thousands of years.
黄金价值千年
It seems that the two
这两者好像本来就
have nothing in common at all.
不是一回事吧
You can't just deny the eternity of love
得不到爱情
for you are not loved.
就否认它的永恒
Well,
这位同学
that's just
你是吃不到葡萄
sour grapes.
说葡萄酸吧
I've been in love twice.
我谈过两段恋爱
How about you?
请问阁下的恋爱经验是
Time is up.
时间到
Calm down.
消消气
I'll teach them a lesson.
我收拾他们
The topic is
辩题
whether the world is a contingency
世界是偶然的
or certainty?
还是必然的
Your turn.
你的
Start!
开始
The world is a contingency.
世界当然是偶然的
If the world is a certainty,
如果是世界是必然的
please give me some examples on
那请对方举例论证
absolute certainty.
什么是绝对必然的存在
The world is an absolute certainty.
世界是必然存在
You are changing the concepts.
你这是偷换概念啊
In your context,
在你的语境里
the world and the certainty are the same stuff.
世界和存在是一个概念
Then your answer can be summarized as
那你的回答
the certainty is a certainty.
就是存在是存在
Isn't this nonsense?
这不一句废话吗
The world is full of contingencies.
世界是偶然的
Because the world is complicated,
因为世界足够复杂
which leads to the continuous occurrence
导致随机事件的
of random events.
不断发生
This is exactly the contingency of the world.
这才是世界的偶然性
Everything has its cause and effect.
凡事都有因果
You are just an ordinary mortal.
你一个凡人
It is not surprising that you think the world is complicated.
当然觉得世界是复杂的
Well, how do you think
那么请问
Dmon de Laplace?
您认同拉普拉斯妖吗
Dmon de Laplace.
拉普拉斯妖
It is assumed that this demon
是假设这个妖怪
knows the information
知道宇宙中的
of every elementary particle
每一个的
in the universe,
基本粒子的信息
so it can predict
所以它可以预知
the future.
所有的未来
But quantum mechanics
但是量子力学已经证明
has proved that
这件事情
this is impossible.
是不可能发生的
Time itself is meaningless
在微观世界里
in the microcosm,
时间本身就没有意义
so how could prediction be carried out?
那何谈预测呢
Just now, you said contingency
你刚才说偶然的意思是
means randomness.
随机发生
But if
可是如果
time is not exist,
时间都不存在的话
how could randomness
那请问随机是
happen?
如何发生的
Does it have to be
是不是必须建立在
based on the existence of time?
时间存在的基础上呢
Contingency is
偶然性是
presented at the macro level.
呈现在宏观层面的
For example,
就比如说
I'm clarifying my point now,
我现在在阐述我的观点
but I cannot predict
但是我根本就无法预测
how will you refute my opinions.
你该是怎么回击我
But the certainty is reflected in that
可必然就体现在
you will lose to me for sure.
你一定会输给我
Time is up.
时间到
See.
看吧
You'll lose to me.
我就说你一定会输给我
Nan Bei
南北
Take a break.
你休息会儿
It's on me.
姐们儿办他
Dango
团子
Calm down. Calm down.
冷静 冷静
Sorry.
对不起
I didn't perform well enough today.
我今天发挥失常了
Relax. Relax.
放松 放松
It's okay.
没事没事啊
Not surprising.
意料之中
Don't worry. Don't worry.
不用担心 不用担心
It's normal.
很正常
Ah?
啊啊
I'm very curious that
我特好奇
what's wrong
你跟刘彦泽
with you and Liu Yanze.
到底什么仇什么怨呐
Lose my love forever.
永失我爱
Rivals in love?
情敌呀
Not that kind of love.
是大爱
Oops.
哎哟
Forget it.
你可算了吧
You can't win him in the debate.
你又辩不过他
And you didn't
那你不还是
win Yin Nan either.
被殷楠气够呛嘛你
What is the point of
你说咱俩
us being here every day?
天天在这图啥呢
It is so hard.
太难了
It doesn't matter that we win or lose.
失败不重要
What matters is
重要的是
that we should
我们要从失败中
learn from our failures.
吸取经验教训
Dango
团子
Ah?
啊
You need to focus on
以后你要好好训练
the training of making conclusions.
结辩了
I make the conclusion?
我结辩
I'm the first debater.
我是一辩
Nan Bei and Xiaoyu work well together,
南北小鱼他们配合默契
so they can be the second debater and the third debater.
最适合二辩三辩了
You need to ......
所以你要好好把
I can't.
我不行
You all saw
我刚刚的实力
my performance just now.
你们也有目共睹了
Will you rest assured
你们放心把
to let me be the fourth debater?
四辩的大旗交给我吗
I think
我觉得
we should invite a qualified one.
我们还是得找个四辩
It's not that easy.
哪儿那么容易呀
I'll discuss it with Sa.
我会去跟小撒商量的
You just continue to
你们好好
prepare the competitions.
准备比赛就可以了
What are you doing?
同学干嘛呢
The class isn't over yet.
没下课 回去
No?
没下课
Sorry. Sorry, Miss.
对不起 对不起老师
I thought I was hearing the bell just now.
我幻听了
Me, too.
我也听下课铃响了
Well.
不是
The teacher has called the roll already.
已经点过名了
Boy and girls.
同学们
The CET-4
四级考试
is around the corner.
马上就要开始了
You need to cherish every second
你们要抓紧
to get well-prepared for the exam.
背单词做真题
I'm not scaring you that
不是老师吓唬你们
you should pass the exam as soon as possible.
四级能早过就早过
By the time you're a junior or senior,
等到大三大四
you won't remember
这四级词汇表上的单词
a single word on this list.
你们一个都不记得了
Help me.
教教我
I'm busy.
我没空
I'll teach Qing and Dango.
我还得教小晴跟团子呢
Teach me, please.
你教教我 教教我
I have no time.
我没空
Okay. Okay. Okay.
教教教 教教教
Nan Bei
南北
Mr. Director
主任
Though I've been late for class a lot lately,
我最近是迟到有点多
I really ......
但我真
We'll discuss that later.
你的事情一会儿再说
You keep an eye on
你们寝室马楠
your roommate Ma Nan and
四级报名的时候
make sure he must register for CET-4 this time.
你得给我盯着点
Last year, he didn't graduate
去年就是因为没报名
just because of this.
所以没毕业
This is a waste
这一年年的
of school resources.
多浪费学校资源
He didn't register for the exam last year?
他去年也没报名
Does CET-4
他 他是对四级有什么
cast a shadow on him?
阴影吗
The shadow is casted through experiences.
阴影是需要培养的
He didn't enter for the exam once.
五年考都没考过一次
How could the shadow be casted on him?
哪来的阴影啊
Okay. I'll keep an eye on him.
行 我盯着点
I got it.
我盯着点
What did you say just now? Who's late?
你刚说迟到什么
No. Nobody.
没 没事
See you, Mr. Li.
我走了 李主任
You got kicked out of school?
你被劝退了
I have to pool money to retake the courses.
凑重修费
But this ......
不是这
This is good stuff.
这可是好东西
What a pity to sell it.
卖了多可惜呀
Why don't you just enter for the CET-4 examination
你要不就把四级考了呗
and graduate this year?
顺利毕业
Your parents will certainly give you money.
你爹妈肯定给你钱啊
Does Mr. Li ask you to persuade me?
老李让你来劝我的
You just do me a favor,
你就当行行好
so that he won't come and bother me again.
别让他再来烦我了好吗
Okay.
行
Then I'll sign you up for the exam.
那我给你报了啊
I forgot my student number.
我学号忘了
You have been here for five years.
你上了五年学
You told me you forgot your student number?
你学号忘了
I've been here for five years.
我这大五了
I'm too old to remember it.
一把年纪 我能记住吗
Then tell me
那你把你身份证号
your ID number.
告诉我
I can't remember the student number which consists of just 10 numbers.
我十位的学号都记不住
How could I remember the ID number which consists of 18 numbers?
我还十八位的身份证号
You must be joking.
你开玩笑
Fine.
行
I'll figure it out for you.
那我给你找
As your good friend,
兄弟一场
I can't let you give up on yourself.
不能看你堕落呀
Okay. Figure it out for me.
那你帮我找
Okay.
嗯
Okay. Then you help me sell all these.
那行 你先把这些卖了
I've got some stuff to do.
然后我出去一趟
Wait. Sell these to whom?
不 我卖给谁呀
The peddler who collects scrap
就门口那个收违章建筑
at the school gate.
收废品那个